Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1791-1806; 18 Linear feet
  - Letters: 1796 D-P (Box -)
    - Letters: G-Heath, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including Gardner & Swain, Harvey Hickley, J. Harvey, and Thomas Hazard. Most correspondence is in regards to regular business matters, though Hickley did write a letter to "Charles Doughty & Sons" rather than "Alsop & Hicks".
      Ships Mentioned:Sally, Pearl
    - Letters: Hi-Huttleston, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including Isaac Howland, James Howland, George Hussey, and Joseph Hudson. Howland discusses a misunderstanding between Captain Grinnell and other individuals. Howland describes how Grinnell is demanding 90 pound sterling to travel to London, but others claim that it was understood in his contract that he could be sent to any port in Europe. James Howland asks Hicks to give money to an associate as payment for anchorage. George Hussey expains to Hicks that his sister died, and therefore his order would be delayed. The remainder of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned:Columbia
    - Letters: J-L, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including Gilbert & Jenkins, John Jenkins, Marshall Jenkins, R. Jenkins, and Thomas Jenkins. Correspondence is in regards to regular business matters, with extensive correspondence from John Jenkins.
      Ships Mentioned:Unity, Hazard
    - Letters: M, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including Frances Macy and George McConnell. Correspondence is predominantly in regards to regular business matters, and primarily talks about the shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned:Defiance,
    - Letters: N, P (except Pennock), 1796 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including extensive correspondence with individuals with the surname Paddock, especially Daniel Paddock. Correspondence is predominantly in regards to bills and shipping.
    - Letters: Pennock, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from George Pennock. While primarily regarding regular business matters, this correspondence covers topics such as dates of payment, chartering vessels, the fluctuating price of coffee, and costs of goods.
  - Letters: 1796 R-Z (Box -)
    - Letters: R, 1796 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including Jacob Randolph; Rhodes & Briggs; Rathbone, Benson & Co.; and Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. Correspondence between Rhodes & Briggs is predominantly from Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada. The correspondence between Rathbone, Benson, & Co. somewhat chronicles the beginning of the working relationship between Rathbone and Hicks, starting with Rathbone introducing himself to Hicks and continuing on to topics regarding shipping and finances.
    - Letters: R; Rotch & Sons, William; Ruketson & Sons, Daniel, 1796 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including William Rotch & Sons, and Daniel Ruketson & Sons, of New Bedford, MA. This correspondence is predominantly about regular business matters and discusses finances and the shipment of goods.
    - Letters: S-Z, 1796 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including David Starbuck, Francis Turner, and Caspar Voght. The correspondence is predominantly in regards to finances and goods shipped. Included in this folder is a log of debits and credits for Philip Sansom and the ship Ann, captained by Joseph Cartwright. Caspar Voght, of Hamburg, Germany, is particularly interested in the changing price of rice.
      Ships Mentioned:Pearl
  - Letters: 1797 A-F (Box -)
    - Letters: Cropper & Benson, 1797-1799 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Contrary to the rest of the organization of this series, this folder includes correspondence with the British merchant house of Cropper & Benson over a number of years. It primarily covers the creation and dissolving of different economic partnerships.
    - Letters: A, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Alden, Howard Allen, and Alstorphius Von Hemirt. It is unknown why Von Hemirt is filed with A surnames. The correspondence with John Alden is primarily concerned with the procurement and shipping of dry goods such as flour, pork, and beef. Howard Allen discusses in one letter how he was prevented from entering port at Amsterdam, and had to find an alternative route to deliver his goods. In one letter from Von Hemirt, he discusses peace negotiations between England and France, and how that would have an effect on trade.
      Ships Mentioned: Commerce
    - Letters: B-Blow, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Frances Barker, James Barker, and Tim Bellnap. The correspondence is mostly in regards to regular business matters, and includes discussions of shipments of goods such as molasses, tobacco, and cotton fabrics.
      Ships Mentioned:Wymouth, Brilliant
    - Letters: Boltch-Butler, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including a large number of letters to Hicks from Robert & John Bolton regarding shipments of cotton from Georgia. There is also a large amount of correspondence with individuals with the surname Bunker. While most correspondence talks about the price and shipping of goods, some speculate about changing prices based on the political climate in France and England. There is also a significant amount of correspondence with James Burrill, Jr. regarding the start of a court case in the Circuit Court against a Mr. Russell. It appears this case is in regards to non-payment of a bill.
      Ships Mentioned:Elizabeth, Belona, Polly
    - Letters: C (Except Coffin), 1797 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John & Isaac Carroll, Joseph Chase, Amy and John Childs, and Daniel Crommelin & Sons. Most of the correspondence is in regards to normal business endeavors. Amy Child also wrote a letter requesting Hicks to inform her if her husband has yet arrived in New York and has contacted him.
      Ships Mentioned:Eliza, Eagle, George
    - Letters: Coffin, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from multiple individuals with the surname Coffin. This includes Thadeus Coffin, Mark Coffin, Shubel Coffin, and more. The contents of this folder are all in regards to shipping, mostly whale oil, spermaceti candles, and cotton.
      Ships Mentioned:Constitution, Hope
    - Letters: D, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including J. Davis, John Delano, Thomas Delano, and Thomas Dickason & Co. The correspondence is comprised of letters regarding normal business matters.
      Ships Mentioned:John, Ann
    - Letters: E, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Killey Elridge and Solomon Ellings. This correspondence predominantly relates to regular business matters, focusing on the buying and selling of goods-mostly whale oil and spermaceti candles.
      Ships Mentioned:Thorn, Sally
    - Letters: F (Except Forbes), 1797 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Fish & Maxfeld; Samuel & Meers Fishers, and George Folger. Most of the correspondence is in regards to normal business matters. Correspondence from Philip & Anthony Felichey discuss how the French military had been garrisned in Leghorn (Liviorno, Italy), how a treaty has been signed in Bologna, Italy, and the army has been removed-which give Philip & Anthony hope for increased trade with the region. There is a large amount of correspondence with Samuel & Meers Fishers, mostly regarding shipping. There is one letter that states that they are going out of the country with their families and children because there is a "sickness" (probably yellow fever) going through Philadelphia. There is also a letter from George Folger, a cashier, revoking Hicks's power of attorney, that had been given to him after a robbery of the bank that employed Folger.
      Ships Mentioned:Franklin, Nancy
    - Letters: Forbes, Edward, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Edward Forbes of Dublin, Ireland. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the shipment of goods from Ireland to the US and the sale of American goods, especially flaxseed, in Ireland. The correspondence also includes an announcement of the defeat of the Spanish fleet, with Forbes discussing the size of the armadas, the number of ships captured, and how the Spanish admiral in chief was killed. He discusses how trade is exceedingly dull in Dublin, and how individuals are buying in small portions rather than in bulk. Forbes also asks Hicks to please find Mr. Patrick Wall or a family member and serve them with a subpoena regarding debts owned in Drogheda, Ireland. Lastly, Forbes discusses waiting for the Germans and French to make peace with England, and how that would influence trade in the region. There are multiple duplicate letters and copies in this folder.
      Ships mentioned: Thomas, Revolution, Polly, Benjamin, Nancy
  - Letters: 1797 G-M (Box -)
    - Letters: G, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, predominantly regarding the settling of debts and the delivery of goods.
    - Letters: H (Except for Hussey), 1797 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients including B. Hammond, Harvey & Leaky, T. Hazard, Isaac Howland & Sons, Joseph Howland, and Benjamin Hunting. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to settling accounts and the shipment of goods. One letter by Joseph Howland discusses Howland's fear of a possible war between France and Spain.
      Ships Mentioned: Franklin, Minerva, Polly, Peggy
    - Letters: Hussey, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence with individuals with the surname Hussey including George Hussey, Joseph Hussey, Lydia Hussey, and William Hussey. The correspondence primarily regards shipments of goods.
      Ships mentioned: Suffolk, Minerva, Elizabeth
    - Letters: J, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      This letter includes correspondence between Isaac Hicks and clients including Jonathan Jenkins of Nantucket, Massachusetts. His correspondence is in regards to the shipping and sale of whale oil and whale products.
      Ships mentioned: Liberty, Minerva
    - Letters: Jenkins, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from individuals with the surname of Jenkins including Marshal Jenkins & Sons, Elisha Jenkins, Robert Jenkins, and Thomas Jenkins & Sons. A majority of the letters are in relation to payment of bills or shipment of goods-especially whale oil, spermaceti candles, seal skins, and salt. A letter from Thomas Jenkins & Sons discusses the dissolving of Thomas Jenkins & sons, and how a new firm has been founded under the same name with the partners Thomas Jenkins, Frederick Jenkins, and Thomas Jenkins, Jr. It also discusses how Elisha and Gilbert Jenkins have found a new partnership under the name Elisha Jenkins & Co.
      Ships mentioned: Revolution, Polly, American Hero
    - Letters: K-L, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients. A letter from J. Keefe says that both he and Hicks are claiming the same chest as their property. Keefe's claim is corroborated by Harvey & Lecky. A letter from The Bank of the United States discusses the arrangement for receiving dividends and remitting them to London. Correspondence from Seth Lothrop discusses a Mr. Lovel and how "he is considered a very bad character by his relatives, whom as well as strangers, he has swindled." A majority of the correspondence is in regards to payment of debt and the shipment of goods such as tobacco, cotton, indigo, and linen.
      Ships mentioned: Pearl, Nancy, George
    - Letters: M, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients including George McConnell, William Mackay, Jr., Charles Minifie & Co., Jethro Mitchell & Sons, and John Morris. A letter from John McLeod discusses the "failure" of L. Mulford and how this failure has caused issues for McLeod. William Mackay, Jr. writes about his anxiety over the same issue. John Manuery asks Hicks to not consider another party's claim for damages because "the woman was nothing but a passenger." There is also a letter from an R. Moores sent from Honduras, which is not a regular location with which Hicks had correspondence. The letter was mostly in regards to Moores's voyage and other business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Hiram
    - Letters: Macy, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients with the surname Macy including Francis Macy, Ruben Macy, Stephen Macy, and Seth Macy. Francis Macy discusses how the United Insurance Company is ready to settle for the loss of the ship Ann. A letter from S&O Macy discusses the ships Joanna and Warren, describing each ships previous voyages and asking Hicks to procure insurance for both ships.
      Ships Mentioned: Ann, Joanna, Warren
    - Letters: Morgan & Douglass, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Morgan & Douglass of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Their correspondence is primarily in regards to the payment of debts, however there is also correspondence from Morgan & Douglass introducing themselves to Hicks, and some minimal correspondence regarding the shipment of goods upon the ship Mary.
      Ships Mentioned: Mary
  - Letters: 1797 N-Z (Box -)
    - Letters: N-P, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients including Captain Judah Paddock and Stephen Paddock, from whom there is extensive correspondence. Included is a receipt of payment to Paddock from a Richard Denny, as well as correspondence from St. Petersburg, Russia. Also included, attached to a letter from September 11, 1797, is a page of modern notes regarding the correspondence from Paddock. Most of the correspondence is in regards to the purchasing and selling of goods, and the procurement of insurance. Paddock also writes about the extreme difficulty he is having buying and selling goods in Savannah, Georgia saying "you might as well try to sell goods on a desolate island as here at present."
      Ships Mentioned: Oswego, Betsey
    - Letters: Pennock, George, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence from George Pennock of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Isaac Hicks. A majority of the letters are in regards to regular business matters such as shipping and receiving goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Mary, Rose (?)
    - Letters: R, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Daniel Ruketson & Sons, Samuel Rodman. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters, including payment for and shipping of goods. Samuel Rodman writes about an act of Congress changing the days when the circuit court meets, he goes on to discuss a court case he appears to be involved with.
      Ships Mentioned: Franklin
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from the firm Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan of Liverpool, England. In one letter they discuss the failure in Paris, France for peace and how they hope that peace can come soon. In another they discuss their anxiety over the reappearance of yellow fever in Philadelphia. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale of goods in both Europe and the United States.
      Included in this folder is a note "Do Not Film." It is unknown who wrote this note or the conditions under which it was put in the collection. It has subsequently been left in situ.
      Ships Mentioned: Minerva, Franklin, Catherine, Pearl
    - Letters: Rotch, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients with the surname Rotch including Thomas Rotch, William Rotch & Sons. Most of the correspondence is in regard to the sale of whale products.
      Ships Mentioned: Prudence, Lydia, Eliza, Susan
    - Letters: S, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients including Philip Sansom, Charles Sheldon, Pardon Sheldon, Isaac Shearman, Allan Shepherd, and Thomas Swain. A letter from Philip Sansom discussed his happiness that the sloop Ann had been liberated after being captured by the Spaniards. In this letter he also discusses how many US Ships had been condemned by the Spanish after being captured by their privateers. Many other letters from Sansom are in regards to the Ann and how Sansom had not heard word of her, and one relating to her possible condemnation. A letter from Charles Sheldon is addressed from Paramarabo (Paramaribo), Surinam (Suriname) regarding consigning Hicks a 'few' bales of cotton. Many other letters in this folder are in regards to the sale and receipt of goods such as cotton and brandy.
      Ships Mentioned: Ann, Eliza, Foy, Mohawk, John, Polly, Thomas, Liberty
    - Letters: T-Z, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Elkanah Tallman, Stephen Waterman, Benjamin Wheeler, and Samuel Wiswalk. Tallman discusses the weather on a voyage to Greenock, including a long period of gale winds. Caspar Voght discusses how the peace on mainland Europe has put a damper on the markets in the Hamburg area. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to current pricing of goods such as tobacco, coffee, and sugar, as well as the purchase and sale of such goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Commerce, Ohio, Jennet, Swallow, Franklin
  - Letters: 1798 A-G (Box -)
    - Letters: A, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients including John Alden and Howard Allen. A majority of the correspondence is by Allen, and is predominantly in regards to regular business matters such as sale of goods. A letter from Lydia Allen asks Hicks to not collect on her husband's account if he had sent no orders on it, because she had not heard from him in months.
      Ships Mentioned: Howard, Juno
    - Letters: B (Except Bolton, Robert & John), 1798 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Belfourt & Co, Jacob Barker, Robert Bines, Blackiston & Richardson, Richard Blaco, Seth Braley, and Solomon Bunker. A letter from Jacob Barker asks for extensions on payments due, due to the fact that there was an outbreak of "sickness" (most likely yellow fever) in his area. Much of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Minerva, Worrin, Hope
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence from Robert and John Bolton to Isaac Hicks. A majority of the correspondence has to do with the sale and shipment of goods, particularly to Russia, and payment for goods and services.
      Ships Mentioned: Diana, Apollo, Polly, Elizabeth, Rachel
    - Letters: C (Except Coffin), 1798 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including David Callaghan, Edward Carrey, Jr., Carpenter & Harvey, Joseph Chase, and Samuel Coates. Joseph Chase writes to Hicks requesting insurance on his ship in case of capture or condemnation, as he has already insured it against other normal dangers. Samuel Coates congratulates Hicks on the good health of his family after an outbreak of yellow fever.
      Ships Mentioned: Prudence, Warren, Eliza, Perseverance, Nancy
    - Letters: Coffin, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from individuals with the surname Coffin, including Aaron Coffin, Elihu Coffin, Mark Coffin, Micajah Coffin & Sons, Obed Coffin, and William Coffin. Included in this folder is a document of indenture, stating that Elihu Coffin was becoming an apprentice to Adolphus Smith to learn how to be a cooper. Along with this document of indenture is a letter from Adolphus Smith asking Hicks to send Coffin back to him. A letter from Micajah Coffin & Sons discusses the dropping price of whale oil. Obed Coffin discusses the sale of multiple ships, including the Rachel and Polly to new owners
      Ships Mentioned: Ocean, Favourite, Fortitude, Galliot Aborigional, Rachel, Polly, Ruby, Cleopatra, Commerce, Juno
    - Letters: D (Except for De Bauque), 1798 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients including John Delano, Richard Delano, Thomas Delano, Silas Downing, Daniel Drinker, and Henry Drinker. Included is a letter of protest from South Carolina documenting the loss of the ships Ann and Susan. This letter discussed the routes the ships took as well as weather patterns during the voyage that caused damage to the ships. The rest of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Rebecca, Commerce, Ann, Susan
    - Letters: De Bauque, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence from the Brothers DeBauque to Isaac Hicks. Included is a list of debits and credits between Epaphras Jones and the Brothers De Bauque. There is also an "Articles of Agreement" document between Jones and De Bauque, and a French Language document. There are also multiple accounts of sales. Much of the correspondence is in regard to opening trade between the United States and France, as well as the goods, such as cotton, that were shipped between the two countries.
      Ships Mentioned: Thomas, Suffolk
    - Letters: E, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Killey Eldredge. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the voyages and cargo of the ship Minerva.
      Ships Mentioned: Minerva
    - Letters: F (Except for Fisher & Forbes), 1798 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including P. Fish, Fish & Mayfield, Mary Foster, John Fry & Co., and Thomas & Joshua Fisher. Included in one of P. Fish's correspondence is a letter stating that Captain Mayhew called Isaac Hicks a "worthless shuffling good for nothing fellow". The letter from Fish praises Hicks for writing a letter to diffuse the situation, but also informs Hicks that it did not work.
    - Letters: Fisher, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      This folder contains correspondence from Samuel Fisher to Isaac Hicks. Much of the correspondence is in regard to flaxseed being shipped on the Minerva. The correspondence also discusses goods such as tobacco, coffee, brandy, wine, and staves.